<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Anenta Waste</title>
    <description>Simple Waste Management Solutions</description>
    <link>http://localhost:4000/</link>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Fri, 20 Mar 2020 12:48:08 +0000</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 20 Mar 2020 12:48:08 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v3.8.5</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>We're going through 1,000 GPs' waste bins. Well, somebody's got to!</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;We’re going through 1,000 GPs’ waste bins. Well, somebody’s gotto!“Do you mind if I have quick look in your bin please?” It’s not the usual way to end a business meeting – but it’s becoming a matter of course for the Anenta team when visiting GPs!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition to the compliance audits we are conducting, we are also supporting the NHS Sustainable Development Unit, by assessing more than 1,000 GPs’ bins in what’s grandly called a ‘compositional audit’. In normal language, that means we are finding out whether different types ofwaste are being segregated effectively, as well as determining how much of it is recyclable and how much is infectious waste that needs dealing with in specific ways.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We believe this is the first time this has been done on such a big scale. Weonly know of ten primary care locations have been regularly monitored over the past decade on the assumption that this was representative across the whole NHS, but that was a pretty big assumption.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anenta people already spend a lot of time visiting GPs all over the countrydoing compliance audits for the NHS. We’ve now agreed that we will also do one of these compositional audits while we’re on the premises. We’re doing them for free, rather than charging the NHS extra – which seems fair to us in the interests of the greater good.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The whole project is going to take about a year, but the brilliant thing is that because we are as usual using Vector, our proprietary online waste management system, to log and analyse the data, the NHS can check in whenever they like to look at emerging trends. It’s another great example of Anenta being able to facilitate true partnerships that drive efficiency and sustainability.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 03 May 2019 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/2019/05/03/we-are-going-through-1000-gps-waste-bins.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2019/05/03/we-are-going-through-1000-gps-waste-bins.html</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Anenta takes on waste management services for GPs across NHS England SE Region after successfully implementing pharmacy service in same area</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Following the successful implementation of pharmacy services across South East England, Anenta has now been successful in expanding its service to GPs on behalf of the region’s CCGs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since being awarded the contract, Anenta has analysed usage data across all locations and identified over £1m of waste within the system. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All new CCG contracts for Anenta’s end-to-end waste management service run from 1 April, covering 559 locations across 17 CCGs in Surrey, Sussex and Kent. The service encompasses operational management, data validations and invoice approval, compliance auditing and setting sustainable efficiency drives which will meet economic and environmental targets within the NHS as a whole.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anenta’s Managing Director Graham Flynn commented: “This is about using Anenta’s online waste management platform, Vector, to facilitate a partnership relationship between the GPs and Pharmacies, NHS, and CCGs and the waste contractors, that brings with it as near total transparency as possible. We can, between us, achieve greater efficiencies, compliance and sustainability - so long as nothing is hidden and that producers and disposal companies play by the rules.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The aim is to liberate teams in GPs and pharmacies to spend more time on clinical care and worry less about how to dispose of their waste sustainably and cost-effectively. CCGs benefit from standardisation in communications, training packages and auditing to make sure they are all compliant, and the economies of scale under which services are delivered and efficiency measures deployed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Anenta is also taking on the management of the waste contracts that have been centrally procured. We know that these contacts are not necessarily as efficient as they could be, so we are making them super-efficient within the remit given to us.”&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 01 Apr 2019 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/2019/04/01/anenet-takes-on-waste-management-service-for-gps-across-nhse-es-region.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2019/04/01/anenet-takes-on-waste-management-service-for-gps-across-nhse-es-region.html</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>The true cost of the clinical waste disposal row</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;The recent airing of issues surrounding the disposal of NHS clinical waste have sparked a debate about whether sufficient capacity exists for its disposal via incineration where appropriate. While this debate continues to divide those in the industry, one positive can be drawn from the situation, which is that the issue has now been forced into the public domain and media spotlight. It is a wake-up call and one which some will believe is long overdue.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The fact that patient numbers are increasing year on year, and that some form of waste is generated during each clinical interaction, cannot be ignored. The amount of waste will inevitably rise, and the issue of capacity will ultimately have to be resolved. We are therefore pleased to see the issue being discussed at national level, and hope this will lead to long-term solutions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, while the capacity debate continues, in its shadow a legitimately worrying practice may be taking place as a direct result of the action against HES.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;br/&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Is profiteering taking place in the wake of the clinical waste row?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Profiteering is defined as ‘disproportionately large or grossly unfair profit, generated often through manipulation of prices, abuse of dominant position, or by exploiting a bad or unusual situation such as temporary scarcity.’&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Recent events could certainly be described as ‘bad or unusual’ and have resulted in ‘temporary scarcity’ in the form of reduced competition.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It has been suggested that some organisations are using the sudden reduction in competition and pressure upon existing incineration capacity to dramatically increase their cost per tonne. There is usually no governmental control over profiteering unless it involves illegal means, so while the price rises some service users claim to be facing may not be illegal, questions need to be raised regarding the ethics of placing additional financial strain on an already stretched health service which ultimately impacts upon the public purse and patient care.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So far, the media has focused on how the NHS will be adversely affected by the revelations about clinical waste disposal. While we appreciate the headline appeal of a taxpayer-funded service being forced to over-spend, we feel attention should also be drawn to the potential impact on private healthcare providers, including care homes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As we have previously discussed, more than 400 care home businesses have collapsed in the lastdecade, and according to one accountancy firm, the number of care home insolvencies almost doubled in 2017/18.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With an aging population in the UK, care home businesses should be benefitting from the shift in demographic, but due to cuts in local authority budgets and the rising costs associated with the care industry, they are struggling.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;br/&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Profiteering must stop&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At Anenta we believe that profiteering is unethical and such activity should cease immediately to prevent creating further financial problems for healthcare providers in both the public and private sectors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We take pride in the amount of money we have helped care homes and other private sector organisations to save over the years through effective, efficient waste management and are acutely aware of the unnecessary pressure that increased waste management costs will place upon them. As Anenta strives to rebuild trust in the waste management industry, we are naturally concerned about the negative impact upon all stakeholders. Most importantly though, we want to assure our existing clients that we are committed to maintaining the highest levels of customer service, procuring cost effective waste management contracts and seeing a fair price for an appropriate level of service delivered. New clients can also be confident that they will be offered the same affordable, tailored service that underpins Anenta’s offer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our goal has always been to offer every client a bespoke service that provides the very best value for money, and that is what we will continue to do, driving new efficiencies in waste management.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 07 Nov 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/2018/11/07/the-true-cost-of-the-clinical-waste-disposal-row.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2018/11/07/the-true-cost-of-the-clinical-waste-disposal-row.html</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Investment Needed to Secure Better Value for the NHS</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Recent national media coverage highlighting issues surrounding the disposal of NHS clinical waste has painted a very unpleasant picture of a system in chaos. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is unfortunate that despite information being made available about what this waste comprised, in many cases the public has been presented with an image of body parts awaiting incineration, being stockpiled. In fact, this specific type of clinical waste constitutes less than 1% of the total volume. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Clinical waste is an often overlooked but inevitable result of treating millions of people every year. Some form of waste is generated during each clinical interaction with a patient and the number of interactions is rising every year. The volume of waste generated is therefore also increasing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Clinical waste cannot simply be disposed of or recycled like most domestic or commercial waste, in every case it requires specialist treatment, one such method being high-temperature incineration.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Recent events have brought to the fore, the question of whether the UK’s high-temperature incineration capacity is sufficient to handle the volume of waste produced not just today, but in the coming years, as waste volumes continue to rise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This debate about capacity looks set to continue. Amid calls for greater infrastructure, the Environment Agency have stated that there is sufficient incineration capacity in the UK. In industry, the field is divided, some adamant that incineration capacity is in fact decreasing. To some degree, the conclusion drawn depends on the way in which one considers the issue and whether the focus is upon the operators’ permitted capacity versus their operational capacity or indeed commercial interests.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is also appropriate to consider at this juncture, why permit changes have been granted to Healthcare Environmental Services (HES) competitors, despite similar requests from HES being denied.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whatever conclusion is drawn, the current situation is clearly not an advantageous one for the customer, in this and most cases, the NHS. Indeed, it has become apparent that a number of clinical waste contractors have sought to profit from the current situation by increasing their standard tonnage rates, the reduced level of competition leaving the NHS with fewer options and little choice but to pay what is at best, an unfair price. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Such practices are short-sighted and ultimately can only impact upon the industry negatively, lowering its reputation further still. Now more than ever, it is fair and transparent pricing that is required for an appropriate level of servicing. This ethos is at the heart of Anenta’s business model and we will continue to work with our clients to mitigate the impact of poor practice and deliver best value for our clients.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many people already familiar with NHS waste disposal may not be surprised by the difficulties the sector now faces and the current disposal challenges are clearly a matter of concern for all parties involved. The issue highlights two key points however: the need for a more robust risk assessment and management process in the NHS and whether investment is now required as a matter of urgency to boost capacity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Change within NHS is required too, to achieve best value. Arguably one of the most effective means by which the NHS could improve upon the issues highlighted is to overhaul the way in which clinical waste contracts are procured.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The need for changes in the procurement process has been highlighted very clearly in fact by recent litigation between the NHS and leading clinical waste contractors. Such change will be welcomed by the industry’s trade associations with many of the key stakeholders waiting for exactly this in order to demonstrate real innovation and drive new efficiencies in waste management which the existing process effectively curtails. As a matter of urgency then, the NHS needs to move away from the race-to-the-bottom evidenced through e-auctions and assess the quality of service it will receive in a more robust manner.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Such a change in the procurement process, delivered in tandem with more effective, proactive contract management, will see a significant improvement in service levels as well as compliance. It will also enable the NHS to improve its risk assessment process, identifying issues such as those now being reported, much further in advance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ageing infrastructure, the impact of zero waste to landfill policies and limited high-temperature incineration capacity have been cited as the underlying cause for recent events. While this debate will continue, it is clear there is very little slack in the system as capacities are held for commercial reasons and planned or unplanned shutdowns. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When one considers the bigger picture however beyond this debate, it is clear that with the appropriate open discussion and investment, the UK’s clinical waste disposal capacity could be increased significantly. Critically, this increased disposal capacity would mean new operators in the market place, greater competition and greater transparency allowing the NHS to secure a fair price for an appropriate level of service. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This can only benefit the NHS and ultimately secure better value for the public purse.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 12 Oct 2018 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/2018/10/12/investment-needed-to-secure-better-value-for-the-nhs.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2018/10/12/investment-needed-to-secure-better-value-for-the-nhs.html</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Wasted millions could save Care Homes from closure</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;With £20bn a year in real terms by 2023/4 pledged to NHS England, the social care sector now
awaits a similar windfall, but additional funding is not the panacea many would like to think.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And while social care leaders await the now long overdue green paper, Care Home Groups across
the UK are facing an increasingly difficult challenge as they strive to keep individual care homes
operating profitably and safely.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More than 400 care home businesses have collapsed this decade – 74 in 2015, 75 in 2016 – it is a
trend that shows little sign of slowing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But the widely reported lack of funding from local authorities as well as rising overheads is only part
of the issue, millions continue to be wasted, on waste.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Savings of 45% for individual care homes, against current waste management costs, could easily be
achieved by the majority of Care Home Groups willing to work collaboratively and adopt new, more
efficient working practices.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anenta’s current activity and review of waste management practices at Care Home Groups across
the UK has highlighted that the majority of individual care homes have outdated contracts in place.
These are normally subject to annual price increases and more often than not are incorrectly
specified.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This means that the majority of Care Home Groups are paying for waste management services which
are either not fit for purpose financially, or do not deliver the specific services care homes require,
adding further strain to an already stressed system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By working collaboratively, instead of procuring services for individual homes, Care Home Groups
could also leverage the total volume of waste produced which would enable costs to be reduced
further still.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Investment in social care is critical, that is without doubt. But whatever proposals and promises of
funding result in the coming months, Care Home Groups will benefit significantly by implementing
real change in operating practice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now is the time for group managers to be developing the appropriate waste management
documentation, driving behavioural change in staff and creating new long-term strategies, working
with waste management contract partners to ensure services are procured effectively, specified
accurately and delivered efficiently.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 22 Aug 2018 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/2018/08/22/wasted-millions-could-save-care-homes.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2018/08/22/wasted-millions-could-save-care-homes.html</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>The procurement challenge in the NHS</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Millions of pounds of tax payers money could be saved if more efficient waste management
practices were adopted in the public and private sector, the majority of savings coming from the
NHS.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anenta’s analysis of waste management contracts across the NHS has highlighted a serious
disconnect between those responsible for procuring waste management contracts and their
understanding of the NHS’s waste management requirements.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Contracts are therefore incorrectly specified from the start and the result is that many Trusts are
paying for waste management services which are either not fit for purpose financially, or do not
deliver the specific requirements including innovative efficiencies, adding further strain to an already
stressed system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Correct specification of waste management contracts equates to improved operational efficiency
and is a real alternative to cuts which impact directly upon front line services.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The limitations of the NHS procurement framework itself presents another issue. The provision of
high value services where contracts are greater in value than £118,133pa, are subject to a Supply,
Services and Design Contract standard framework. This framework works against the very thing it is
designed to secure – best value for the Trust.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Typically the public sector issue standard and out-dated specifications resulting in recycled tender
responses being returned. These out-dated responses therefore do not take into account any new
industry efficiencies as they do not form part of the specification.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Meanwhile bidders are always cautious of being innovative within their bids as there could be the
possibility that the evaluation teams could score them negatively for not directly responding to the
requirements within the specification.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In effect it means there is a catch 22 situation where the bidder feels they meet the specification
could go beyond, demonstrating real innovation, but are unwilling to risk losing the opportunity by
thinking outside the box.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Compounding the issue is the fact that once the service has been procured, it is often not managed
effectively and in significant number of cases, it is not managed at all by the customer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many Trusts rely upon contractors to self-manage and indeed, for some, there is no viable
alternative. A lack of waste contract management expertise combined with a lack of ownership
within the NHS means that in many instances it falls to inexperienced staff, to handle waste
management contracts – something which they have neither the time nor appropriate expertise to
do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To help tackle these challenges and enable the NHS realise the benefits and savings that are
possible, Anenta has already invested more than £1m developing its proprietary online waste
management platform.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Key to the success of this new system, is the empowerment of all stakeholders, an integral
component of Anenta’s vision – creating and maintaining trust between the customer and service
provider, underpinned by a correctly specified service.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In four years, this new way of working has enabled Anenta to save the NHS over £3.2m on existing
contracts across 19 CCGs. When extrapolated across England, potential savings of £8.75m annually
become apparent. Procurement of new contracts will see this figure increase dramatically by
implementing contract control and accountability through the use of Anenta’s management
platform and expertise.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 31 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/2018/01/31/the-procurment-challenge-in-the-nhs.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2018/01/31/the-procurment-challenge-in-the-nhs.html</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Cut waste, not cut backs</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;The views of Adam Read, Suez external affairs director, in the piece, Cut backs and staffing concerns
leave recycling in the shadows at UK hospitals, made for interesting reading. Interesting, but not
surprising according to Graham Flynn, managing director of Anenta, an independent environmental
services contract management partner.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In fact the only real surprise is that our hospitals have managed to provide the quality of care that
Adam Read enjoyed, for as long as they have, given the millions of pounds which is effectively
thrown away as a result of inneficient waste management practices.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Reflecting on what’s not working in the hospitals he had visited across England, Adam noted how
tight staffing levels were, and specifically, the obvious lack of bins. But is it cuts and staffing concerns
that are creating the waste management issue, or poor waste management that is resulting, in part
at least, in those same cuts?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It would perhaps be a step too far to suggest that improving waste management in the NHS is the
panacea to all ailments, but the reality is that in just 18 months, working as NHS England’s managing
agent for North London Primary Care waste, Anenta has delivered savings of £1.8m, using its unique
proprietary platform to standardise pricing schedules, match customer requirements to contracts
and optimise service provision. In fact in the last four years, this way of working has enabled Anenta
to save the NHS over £3.2m on existing contracts across 19 CCGs. When extrapolated across
England, potential savings of £8.75m annually become apparent. It is clear therefore that improving
the efficiency of waste management is a real alternative to cuts which negatively impact frontline
services.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was also interesting to note that Adam needed to ask nurses and other staff to direct him to the
appropriate bins for different types of waste, which were not readily visible. More significant
perhaps is the fact that while nurses and other front line staff do of course need to dispose of waste,
it should following the provision of training to give an understanding of the different waste types. In
many cases, this training is simply not being provided.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Meanwhile, it is falling to administrative staff from nursing backgrounds to manage the waste
management contracts and the reality is that despite the skilled and proffessional attitude
demonstrated every day by NHS staff across the country, contract management is something these
people have neither the time or expertise to deliver effectively.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Indeed Anenta’s analysis of NHS contracts has highlighted that in the majority of cases, once the
waste management service has been procured, it is not managed effectively and in a significant
number of cases, it is not managed at all by the customer. A lack of contract management expertise
combined with a lack of ownership within the NHS, ultimately means more than simply a lack of the
necessary types of bins or unclear signage as Adam saw. It means low levels of efficiency at best and
high levels of waste and quite possibly front line cuts which could have been avoided, at worst.
Of course I share Adam’s frustration and he is right, a great deal has been done over the years to
identify cost saving opportunities throughout the NHS and one has only to look to Lord Carter’s 2016
report which estimated a saving of £1bn on running costs every year if each NHS trust performed as
well as the best, to see the scale of the opportunity. And he is also absolutely right that Warwick
Hospital, like so many others, would benefit from an audit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, the insight to be gained from such a process will only prove to be of use if other key issues
are tackled, specifically within the procurement process. The current disconnect between those
procuring waste management contracts and their understanding of the NHS’s waste management
requirements is perhaps the first of these. The procurement framework and the limitations it
imposes particularly for higher value contracts is another and once a service has been procured, it
has to be managed by those with the right expertise and appropriate motivation.
Adam also calls for stakeholders to share good and bad practice – again he is right. But clear
ownership is required first – this will drive more effective collaboration between departments and
Trusts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But let’s look beyond the hospitals for moment – aside from an unnecessarily complicated
procurement and a lack of contract management processes within the NHS, change is needed in the
waste management industry too. Trusts are faced with ambiguous pricing from service providers
which is subject to change over time, a lack of clarity concerning contract deliverables and poor
monitoring and communications.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To tackle these issues, Anenta has already invested more than £1m in its proprietary online waste
management platform with the objective of providing every customer with an easy to use system
which delivered a bespoke service and provided best value.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The ability, and capacity to analyse data effectively which this platform has provided has also
enabled Anenta to highlight charges for services that have not been provided by waste management
suppliers for numerous customers. Innapropriate miscellaneous charges totalling over £2m have
been identified by Anenta across its customer base and in the last three years waste contractors
have refunded more than £500,000.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Resources are important and hospital expenditure huge, as Adam noted, making the point that a
relatively small percentage saving could be significant in terms of nursing care and patient access.
Quite right – cutting waste through more effective contract management will help to stop cuts in
other critical areas. But the percentage saving could be a great deal more than many realise. Indeed,
with a step change in procurement and waste management process, the percentage saving could
make a significant contribution to the 2020 overall efficiency savings target of £22bn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And it will help Adam and millions of other patients to continue receiving the care they require from
the front line staff who work so hard to deliver it.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 31 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/2018/01/31/cut-waste-not-cut-backs.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2018/01/31/cut-waste-not-cut-backs.html</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Applauding the NHS funding increase</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Writing for The Observer, Andrew Rawnsley’s article (24.06.18) examined the Theresa May’s
spending pledge for the health service.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is of course right to consider the question of where the £20bn funding boost will come from, but
the extensive, largely negative commentary in the wider press seems a little strange to me. The
reality is that we have now received, what the majority collectively branded the politicians as too
inept to provide, and yet we continue to complain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I applaud the funding increase.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And while those who called so vigorously for funding increases appear to be knocking £20bn as not
enough or too late, perhaps we should instead be saying: &quot;Thank you, let’s get on with spending it
well.&quot;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Throughout my career I have focussed on creating mechanisms for the NHS to be more efficient with
the money it has, without impacting negatively on, and indeed to protect critical front line services.
The question which is most pressing now is perhaps not where the funding will come from but how
does the NHS stop wasting money so that the £20bn can go directly to the front line.
In his 2016 report, Lord Carter noted that NHS trusts spend around £9bn every year buying goods
and services. Operating costs, the report indicated, ranged from £100 to almost £1,000 per square
metre. With such variation between sites and the operating practices of NHS trusts themselves, Lord
Carter estimated a saving of £1bn solely on running costs every year, if each NHS trust performed as
well as the best.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First-hand experience has done nothing to suggest this is not the case. Indeed, it has made me
acutely aware of the significant wastage within the NHS created through inappropriate procurement
practices and a lack of tangible data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Across the NHS there are multiple procurement departments, all of which procure predominantly
the same consumable items, facilities management services, medical equipment or waste disposal
services. Each department decides on the mechanism under which they make these purchases,
therefore all pay a different price for the purchase.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some NHS entities join forces to leverage their joint buying power, however none of the
stakeholders fully agree with the specifications that are issued. This leads to a great deal of
frustration, the wrong product or service being purchased and thus the circle continues.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, even when an NHS organisation has made a good purchase, typically with services,
there remains a significant lack of control over the contracts.
This leads to the contractor potentially overcharging for services not delivered while the NHS
continues to pay the invoices. One of the solutions is better data management.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Having data in a structured format that is easily analysed helps the NHS (the customer) understand
the levels of service, compliance against the contract terms and importantly validate line items on
the submitted invoices.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The reality now is that the NHS could save tens of millions quickly, simply through more effective
procurement and wherever possible, by reusing equipment such as walking aides.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over £300m of unused medicines are disposed of every year at a cost to the NHS. Why is there so
much wastage in this area? Quite simply, because of unclear guidelines and operating standards and
consequently over prescribing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I applaud the £20bn additional funding, but how will this money be utilised and how will the NHS
monitor it to determine whether they are spending it well, considering the significant issues that are
already in play?&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 31 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/2018/01/31/applauding-the-nhs-funding-increase.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2018/01/31/applauding-the-nhs-funding-increase.html</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
